Peppino Mangravite
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Peppino Mangravite papers
1918-1982
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Peppino Mangravite
6.1 linear feet
The Peppino Mangravite papers measure 6.1 linear feet and are dated 1918-1982. They consist of correspondence, subject files, recorded interviews with significant artists and transcripts, writings and notes, miscellaneous records, printed matter, and photographs documenting Mangravite’s career as a painter and educator.
Biographical Note
In 1914, at the age of eighteen, Peppino Gino Mangravite (1896-1978) settled in New York City with his father. The young man had already completed six years of study at the Scuole Techiniche Belle Arti in his native Italy, where coursework included the study of anatomy and Renaissance fresco techniques. Upon arrival in New York, he enrolled at Cooper Union, and by 1917 was studying under Robert Henri at the Art Students League.
Mangravite began his teaching career - one that lasted half a century - as assistant to Hans Peter Hansen at the Hansen School of Fine Arts in New York during the academic year 1918/19. He was an involved and committed teacher who worked equally well with young children and college students. For several summers in the 1920s, he ran summer art camps in the Adirondacks for children and adults. From 1926-1928 Mangravite lived in Washington D.C., where he taught at the Potomac School. The majority of his life was spent in New York where he served on the faculties of Sarah Lawrence College, Cooper Union, the Art Students League, and, most notably, Columbia University. In addition, he spent 1937-38 as head of the art department of Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, and from 1940-1942 taught at the Art Institute of Chicago. Mangravite was active in professional arts and education organizations. He wrote a number of articles about art education and served as chairman of the College Art Association's Committee for the Study of the Practice of Art Courses, 1943-1944.
In addition to teaching studio courses, Mangravite was a working artist. Represented by Dudensing Gallery, and later Rehn Galleries, he exhibited widely throughout the United States, and, occasionally, abroad. He won a number of awards, including a gold medal for mural painting at the Philadelphia Sesquicentennial Exhibition, 1926; the American Gold Medal Purchase Prize, Golden Gate Exposition, San Francisco, 1939; Alice McFadden Eyre Medal for best print, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1946; and a silver medal for mosaic design, Architectural League of New York, 1955. Mangravite was awarded Guggenheim Fellowships in 1932 and 1935, and during that same period was commissioned by the U.S. Treasury Department to paint murals for post offices in Hempstead, N.Y. and Atlantic City, N.J. Other commissions of note include a mural for the Governor's Mansion in the Virgin Islands, and a mosaic mural for the main altar of the Workers' Chapel, St. Anthony's Shrine, Boston, Mass.
Sponsored by Columbia University and with the assistance of the United States Information Agency, Mangravite met with art department heads of several European universities in 1955 to discuss Columbia University's plans for a new arts center. He also interviewed eight artists - Georges Braque, Marc Chagall, Giorgio De Chirico, Marino Marini, Henry Moore, Giorgio Morandi, Georges Rouault, and Graham Southerland -recording their ideas about art, life, and education.
Peppino Mangravite died in 1978.
Scope and Content Note
The Peppino Mangravite papers measure 6.1 linear feet and are dated 1918-1982. They consist of correspondence, subject files, interviews with artists, writings and notes, miscellaneous records, printed matter, and photographs documenting Mangravite's career as a painter and educator.
Series 1: Correspondence includes chronological correspondence documenting Mangravite's career as a painter and educator. Correspondence is with employers, dealers, museums, galleries, collectors, clients, arts and educational organizations, publishers, and other artists. Much of the correspondence is between Mangravite and his dealers, the Dudensing Gallery and the Rehn Galleries, and with other galleries and museums where his paintings were exhibited. Mangravite's mural commissions are also discussed. Additional events documented include Mangravite's two Guggenheim Fellowships and his trip to Europe in 1955 to interview famous artists.
Mangravite's long teaching career is also documented in correspondence with Columbia University, Sarah Lawrence College, Avon School, Fieldston School of the Ethical Culture Schools, Potomac School, Dana Hall School, and the Colorado Springs Fine Art Center. Other topics covered in the correspondence concern Mangravite's published or proposed writings, particularly articles and books reviews, most notably for the Saturday Review of Literature and American Magazine of Art. Mangravite's membership activities in a variety of artists' organizations, such as the College Art Association, the American Society of Painters, Sculptors and Gravers; the American Artists' Congress, and the American Federation of Arts is well-represented in the correspondence.
A list of major correspondents can be found in the series description for Series 1: Correspondence.
Series 3: Interviews with Artists includes audio recordings, transcripts, photographs, notes and reports. During the summer of 1955, Mangravite traveled to England, France, and Italy where he conducted interviews with eight artists - Georges Braque, Marc Chagall, Giorgio De Chirico, Marino Marini, Henry Moore, Giorgio Morandi, Georges Rouault, and Graham Southerland - recording their ideas about art, life, and education. In 1972, Mangravite recorded an interview with Rufino Tamayo in Mexico City, and the two artists were photographed together on that occasion.
Series 4: Writings, Notes, and Lectures consists of articles, papers, talks, lectures, miscellaneous writings, and notes by Mangravite, and a small number of items by other writers. Series 5: Miscellaneous Records includes art work by Mangravite and others, audio/visual records, biographical information, and financial records. Among the printed matter in Series 6 are articles, exhibition announcements, invitations, catalogs, and miscellaneous printed items by and about Mangravite, art-related topics, and other subjects. In Series 7: Photographs, photos of people include Mangravite, students, and other artists. Photos of works of art are of murals and paintings by Mangravite and sculpture by Edgar Britton.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into 7 series:
Series 1: Correspondence, 1918-1977 (Boxes 1-2; 1.75 linear ft.; Reels 5878-5880)
Series 2: Subject Files, 1940-1960 (Box 2; 0.25 linear ft.; Reel 5880-5881)
Series 3: Interviews with Artists, 1955, 1972 (Boxes 3, 8; 0.65 linear ft.; Reel 5881)
Series 4: Writings, Notes and Lectures, 1928-1965 (Box 3; 0.35 linear ft.; Reel 5881)
Series 5: Miscellaneous Records, 1926-1974 (Boxes 4, 8; 10 folders; Reel 5881)
Series 6: Printed Matter, 1918-1982 (Boxes 4-6; 2.65 linear ft.; Reels 5881-5882)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1926-circa 1970 (Boxes 7-8; 0.4 linear ft.; Reel 5882)
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Dudensing Galleries; Frank K.M. Rehn Galleries
Subjects-Topical:
Art -- Study and teaching; Art -- Economic aspects
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Interviews; Works of art
Names:
Moore, Henry, 1898-; Morandi, Giorgio, 1890-1964; Rouault, Georges, 1871-1958; Sutherland, Graham Vivian, 1903-; Braque, Georges, 1882-1963; Chagall, Marc, 1887-; De Chirico, Giorgio, 1888-; Marini, Marino, 1901-; Tamayo, Rufino, 1899-
Provenance
Most of the collection was donated by Peppino Mangravite in 1977. Additional papers were donated in 2003 by his daughter Denise Mangravite Scheinberg that include records documenting Mangravite's 1955 interviews with European artists, a sound recording and photographs of his meeting with Rufino Tamayo in 1972, a motion picture film of Mangravite's painting class at the Potomac School, and a small number of printed items.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Patrons must use microfilm copy.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35mm microfilm reels 5878-5882 in Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Correspondence, 1918-1977, undated, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.75 linear ft.; Reels 5878-5880)
  Chronological correspondence documents Mangravite's career as a painter and educator and is with employers, dealers, museums, galleries, collectors, clients, arts and educational organizations, publishers, and other artists. The majority of the letters are written in English, but some are composed in French and Italian as well. Although primarily business correspondence, there is also a significant amount of personal correspondence with friends, colleagues, and former students. The letters often cover both business and personal topics, as Mangravite seemed to form close relationships with many of the people at the galleries and schools with which he was associated. Correspondence dated from 1918 to the 1950s is comprised mostly of incoming letters. Starting in the 1950s, the correspondence includes more outgoing correspondence, usually in the forms of onion skin copies and handwritten drafts. Correspondence is arranged chronologically, except two folders of undated letters, which are arranged alphabetically by last name of writer. A list of major correspondents follows.
  A large amount of correspondence is between Mangravite and his dealers, the Dudensing Gallery and the Rehn Galleries, and discusses financial agreements, sales, and accounts. There is also correspondence with other galleries and museums where his paintings were exhibited. Mangravite's mural commissions are also discussed in the correspondence. Also found are invitations to participate in exhibitions, notifications of prize awards and artwork sales, invitations to be on juries for art competitions, or miscellaneous requests from fellow artists, fans, collectors, and clients. Significant events documented here include Mangravite's two Guggenheim Fellowships and his trip to Europe in 1955 to interview famous artists.
  Mangravite's long teaching career is also documented in this series. Correspondence is found with Columbia University, Sarah Lawrence College, Avon School, Fieldston School of the Ethical Culture Schools, Potomac School, Dana Hall School, and the Colorado Springs Fine Art Center. Additionally, Mangravite was also a sought-after speaker and his correspondence includes many lecture invitations and requests as well as arrangements for accepted speaking engagements.
  Other topics covered in the correspondence concern Mangravite's published or proposed writings, particularly articles and books reviews, most notably for the Saturday Review of Literature and American Magazine of Art. Also, there is some correspondence with publishers regarding book project ideas and manuscripts. Mangravite's membership activities in a variety of artists' organizations, such as the College Art Association, the American Society of Painters, Sculptors and Gravers; the American Artists' Congress, and the American Federation of Arts are well-represented in the correspondence. Of particular interest is Mangravite's response to an artists' rental policy debate during the 1930s, concerning the payment of rental fees for artworks exhibited in shows and galleries.
  Major Correspondents
  American Artists Congress
  American Federation of Arts
  American Society of Painters
  Arms, John Taylor
  Avon School
  Barr, Alfred
  Barzun, Jacques (Columbia University)
  Bear, Donald J.
  Benson, Emanuel
  Biddle, George
  Burchfield, Charles
  Canaday, John
  Canby, Courtlandt
  Chagall, Marc
  Clancy, John (Rehn Galleries)
  Cole, Sylvan Jr. (Associated American Artists)
  College Art Association
  Colorado Springs Fine Art Center
  Columbia University
  d'Harnoncourt, Rene
  Dana Hall School
  Davis, Stuart
  Dudensing, Richard
  Fieldston School of the Ethical Culture Schools
  Force, Juliana
  Gonzales, Xavier
  Harper & Brothers Publishers
  Knight, Frederick
  Larom, Henry V.
  Lockwood, Ward
  Magafan, Ethel and Jenne and Edward Chavez
  Maldarelli, Oronzio
  Manso, Leo
  Manzella, David
  Moe, Henry Allen
  Mumford, Lewis
  Pearson, Ralph M. (Design Workshop)
  Philips, Duncan
  Picken, George
  Poor, Henry V.
  Potomac School
  Preston, Carol (Potomac School)
  Rehn, Frank K. M.
  Rice, Norman (Art Institute of Chicago)
  Rich, Daniel Catton (Art Institute of Chicago)
  Robinson, Boardman (Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center)
  Roosevelt, Willard
  Root, Edward W.
  Saint-Gaudens, Homer
  Sarah Lawrence College
  Sculptors and Gravers
  Simonson, Lee
  Speicher, Gene
  Sweet, Frederick A. (Portland Art Museum)
  Talbot, William
  Thayer, H. Standish
  Vander Sluis, George
  Watson, Forbes
  Watkins, Franklin C.
  Weston, Harold
  Wilder, Mitchell A. (Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center)
  Wyatt, Stanley
  - Chronological Correspondence, 1918-1951, (29 folders) (Box 1, Reel Reel 5878-5879)
  - Chronological and Undated Correspondence, 1952-1977, undated, (24 folders) (Box 1, Reel Reel 5879-5880)
- Subject Files, 1940-1960, undated, Series 2:; (Box 2; 0.25 linear ft.; Reels 5880-5881)
  Subject files, arranged alphabetically, represent committees, organizations, and conferences in which Mangravite participated as a committee member or speaker. They contain printed matter, minutes, and notes. The file for the American Art Research Council contains painting registration forms completed by Mangravite. The file of printed matter concerning art courses in France and Italy probably was assembled for his daughter, Denise, who studied in Rome during the summer of 1955. Of particular interest is the file titled "Committee for the Study of the Practice of Art Courses, sponsored by College Art Association," which investigated how art was being taught and reported on its findings. Because the members of the committee - George Biddle, Jean Charlot, Bartlett H. Hayes, J. Ward Lockwood, Peppino Mangravite (chairman), Daniel Catton Rich, Boardman Robinson, Edward W. Root, and Franklin C. Watkins - were unable to gather as a body, the work of the committee, including preparation and editing of its final report, was conducted by correspondence.
  - American Academy in Rome, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - American Art Research Council, 1943 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - American Federation of Arts, 1940-1942 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Art Courses in France and Italy, 1955, undated (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Art In Education Conference, Columbia University, 1952 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Columbia University Bicentennial Celebration, Conference on the Arts, 1954 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Committee for Distributing Robert D. Kaufmann's Paintings, 1959-1960 (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Committee for the Study of the Practice of Art Courses, sponsored by College Art Association, 1943-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5880)
  - Committee for the Study of the Practice of Art Courses, sponsored by College Art Association, 1943-1944, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Reel 5881)
- Interviews with Artists, 1955, 1972, Series 3:; (Boxes 3, 8; 0.65 linear ft.; Reel 5881)
  During the summer of 1955, sponsored by Columbia University, and with the assistance of the United States Information Agency, Mangravite traveled to England, France, and Italy, where he met with artists and scholars, and art department heads of several European universities to discuss Columbia University's plans for a new Art Center. He interviewed Georges Braque, Marc Chagall, Giorgio De Chirico, Marino Marini, Henry Moore, Giorgio Morandi, Georges Rouault, and Graham Sutherland. Original audio recordings (7" reel to reel audio tapes) of all interviews except Giorgio Morandi are found here, along with excerpts of Mangravite's conversations with Braque, Chagall, De Chirico, Marini, and Morandi copied for radio broadcast (three 33-1/3 rpm lp recordings). Transcripts of all interviews are included, though there is no English translation of Rouault's interview. Each artist was also photographed with Mangravite on the day of his interview, except for Henry Moore who is represented by a single photograph taken circa 1955. The photographs are filed in this series.
  In 1972, Mangravite recorded an interview with Rufino Tamayo in Mexico City, and the two artists were photographed together on that occasion. No transcript of the recording is among the Mangravite papers.
  Photographs of other artists are filed with Series 7: Photographs, and a manuscript "Language of the Hand and Eye: Artists on Art, Life, and Education," by Mangravite, based on his interviews with European artists, can be found with Series 4: Writings, Notes, and Lectures.
  - "Columbia University's Proposal to Mr. Theodore Streibert, Director of the United States Information Agency, on Professor Peppino Mangravite's Mission Abroad," 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Notes, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - "Professor Peppino Mangravite Reports to Dr. Grayson Kirk, President of Columbia University, on his interviews with artists and scholars in England, France and Italy, May, June, July and August, 1955," 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Transcripts (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Georges Braque" (in French, with English translation and notes), June 19, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Marc Chagall" (in French, with English translation and edited copy), June 26, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Giorgio De Chirico" (in Italian, with English translation), July 9, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Marino Marini" (English translation), July 12, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Henry Moore" (with list of questions), June 7, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Giorgio Morandi" (in Italian, with English translation), July 13, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Georges Rouault" (in French, with list of questions), June 14, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Conversation with Graham Sutherland," June 6, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Sound Recordings (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, June 19, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording; see: Box 8) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, June 19, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Chagall, Marc, June 26, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - De Chirico, Giorgio, July 9, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Marini, Marino, July 12, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Moore, Henry, June 7, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Rouault, Georges, June 14, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Rouault, Georges, June 14, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording; see: box 8) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Sutherland, Graham, June 6, 1955, (7" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Rufino Tamayo and Peppino Mangravite, Conversation in Tamayo's Studio, Mexico City," Febraury 24, 1972, (5" reel) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - DeChirico, Giorgio; Morandi, Giorgio; and Marini, Marino, July 9, 1955, July 13, 1955, July 12, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording; see: box 8) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Photographs (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, June 19, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, June 19, 1955, (duplicates) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges and Mangravite, June 19, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges and Mangravite, June 19, 1955, (duplicates) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, Mangravite, and Darthea Speyer, June 19, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, Mangravite, and Darthea Speyer, June 19, 1955, (duplicates) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Chagall, Marc, June 26, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Chagall, Marc and Mangravite, June 26, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - DeChirico, Giorgio and Mangravite, July 9, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Marini, Marino and Mangravite, July 12, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Moore, Henry, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Morandi, Giorgio, July 13, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Morandi, Giogrio and Mangravite, July 13, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Rouault, Georges and Mangravite, June 14, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Sutherland, Graham and Mangravite, June 6, 1955 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Tamayo, Rufino and Mangravite, February 24, 1972 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Sound Recordings (Box 8 (sol), Reel 5881)
    - Braque, Georges, June 19, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording) (Box 8 (sol), Reel 5881)
    - De Chirico, Giorgio, July 9, 1955; Morandi, Giorgio, July 13, 1955; and Marini, Marino, July 12, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording) (Box 8 (sol), Reel 5881)
    - Rouault, Georges, June 14, 1955, (33-1/3 rpm lp recording) (Box 8 (sol), Reel 5881)
- Writings, Notes, and Lectures, 1928-1962, undated, Series 4:; (Box 3; 0.35 linear ft.; Reel 5881)
  - Articles and Papers By Mangravite (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Dante Through Three Artists' Eyes," circa 1965, (research notes) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "The Idea and the Problem," undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Language of the Hand and Eye: Artists on Art, Life, and Education," undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Mind and Sense Question," undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Relation of Creative Design to an Education in the Humanities," published in College Art Journal, Spring 1952, (French translation) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Miscellaneous Writings By Mangravite (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Book Reviews, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Unidentified Fragments, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Lesson Plan, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Notes and Lists, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Objectives in Teaching Art in the Fieldston School," 1935 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Plan to Help the War Effort, Museums, American Art and Artists, circa 1942-1945 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Report on Art School of the Colorado Springs Fine Arts Center, circa 1938 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Talks/Lectures By Mangravite (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "The American Painter and His Environment," undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "The Artist's Point of View on Art Education," Private School Association of Boston, 1936 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "Directions and Misdirections in American Art," undated, (lecture notes) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "From the Painter's Point of View," Mangravite's contribution to "Freedom of Expression for Artists," a panel discussion sponsored by American Federation of Arts, 1947 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - "The Future of Painting," on ABC Television's "Horizons" (transcript, schedule, publicity), 1951 (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Lecture Notes, circa 1948-1950, undated, (2 untitled lectures) (Box 3, Reel 5881)
    - Talk at the Potomac School, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
  - Writings By Others (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Claude Monet's Painting of a Branch of the Seine near Giverny in the Metropolitan Museum of Art," by Myron David Brenner, 1962, (student paper) (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
    - "Drawing," by Rico Lebrun, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
    - Miscellaneous Notes, undated (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
    - Poems by J.B.L. Godwin, Ann S. V. Mann, and W. A. Weiss, 1928-1955 (Box 3, Reel unfilmed)
    - Review of Mangravite Exhibition at Chappell House by Donald J. Bear, undated (Box 3, Reel 5881)
- Miscellaneous Records, 1926-1974, undated, Series 5:; (Boxes 4, 8; 10 folders; Reel 5881)